• The first line of input specifies N (the number of distinct items) and M (the maximum weight 
limit of the knapsack). You may assume that 1 ≤ N ≤ 100 and 1 ≤ M ≤ 1000. The next N 
lines of input correspond to the N items. Each such line gives four pieces of information 
about an item k: the profit Pk, weight Wk, upper bound Uk, and type Tk. Each of N, M, Pk, 
Wk is a positive integer. Each Uk is either a positive integer or ∞ (which is denoted by –1). 
Each Tk is either ‘C’ (continuous) or ‘I’ (integer). 
 
• The goal is to determine how many copies Xk ≤ Uk of each item k to place in the knapsack in 
order to maximize the total profit of all items in the knapsack. Mathematically, we want to 
solve this optimization problem: 
 
Maximize Z = Σ1 ≤ k ≤ n Pk*Xk 
such that Σ1 ≤ k ≤ n Wk*Xk ≤ M, 
each 0 ≤ Xk ≤ Uk, 
and if Tk = ‘I’ then Xk is an integer. 
 
• The output should consist of the maximum Z and the numbers Xk that achieve this 
maximum Z, each on a separate line. 
 
• Example: N=6, M=22 
 
k Pk Wk Uk Tk         Xk 
1 2  10 3  continuous 0 
2 7  6  10 integer    2 
3 7  8  ∞  continuous 0.5 
4 3  1  4  integer    4 
5 4  2  1  continuous 1 
6 1  9  ∞  integer    0 
 
 Z = 33.5 
 
Input1.txt 
6 22 
2 10 3  C 
7 6  10 I 
7 8  -1 C 
3 1  4  I 
4 2  1  C 
1 9  -1 I 

Output1.txt 
33.5 
0 
2 
0.5 
4 
1 
0 