• This program will begin by reading an input list that contains at most 1024 words, each 
consisting entirely of lowercase letters. Example: 
slot
stop
tips
pins
trap
 
• Next the program will build an undirected graph G such that each vertex of G corresponds to 
an input word, and G has an edge (X,Y) iff word X can be transformed into word Y via the 
following operation: Begin with the letters of word X; optionally insert any one letter, or 
remove any one letter, or replace any one letter with another letter; then optionally permute 
the letters to form the new word Y. Examples: Transform “slot” into “stop” by replacing ‘l’ 
with ‘p’ and then permuting. Transform “stop” into “tips” by replacing ‘o’ with ‘i’ and then 
permuting. Transform “tips” into “pins” by replacing ‘t’ with ‘n’ and then permuting. 

[slot]-[stop]-[tips]-[pins]  [trap]

 
• It will consider both unweighted and weighted versions of graph G. Define weight(X,Y) = the 
minimum possible number of letter insertions, removals, and/or replacements that can 
transform word X into word Y. This weight(X,Y) is called the edit distance between X and Y, 
and it can be computed by dynamic programming. Examples: Weight(“slot”,“stop”) = 2 
because starting with “slot” we can replace ‘l’ with ‘t’ and replace ‘t’ with ‘p’ to obtain “stop”. 
Weight(“stop”,“tips”) = 3 because starting with “stop” we can remove ‘s’, replace ‘o’ with ‘i’, 
and insert ‘s’ at the end to obtain “tips”. Weight(“tips”,“pins”) = 2 because starting with “tips” 
we can replace ‘t’ with ‘p’ and replace ‘p’ with ‘n’ to obtain “pins”. 
 
[slot]-2-[stop]-3-[tips]-2-[pins]  [trap]


• This program will run 3 graph algorithms and generate 3 lines of output as follows: 
 
o Determine the connected components of G, and count the number of vertices in each 
component. Output all the different component sizes in ascending order, along with the 
number of components that have each size. Example: Our graph G has 1 component of 
size 1, and 1 component of size 4. 
Component sizes: {1*1,4*1} 
 
o Compute the shortest unweighted path distance fromeach vertex X to each other vertex Y 
in the same component. Output each distinct finite positive path distance in ascending 
order, along with the number of vertex pairs {X,Y} that are exactly this unweighted distance 
apart from each other. Example: Unweighted graph G has 3 pairs of vertices at distance 1, 
2 pairs of vertices at distance 2, and 1 pair of vertices at distance 3. 
Unweighted distances: {1*3,2*2,3*1} 
 
o Compute the shortest weighted path distance from each vertex X to each other vertex Y in 
the same component. Output each distinct finite positive path distance in ascending 
order, along with the number of vertex pairs {X,Y} that are exactly this weighted distance 
apart from each other. Example: Weighted graph G has 2 pairs of vertices at distance 2, 
1 pair of vertices at distance 3, 2 pairs of vertices at distance 5, and 1 pair of vertices at 
distance 7. 
Weighted distances: {2*2,3*1,5*2,7*1} 
 
• This program should read from standard input stream and write to standard output stream. 
The input might be redirected from a file, and the output might be redirected to a file, but this 
program will be unaware of any file names. Download the provided example files to see the 
precise input and output formats. 
 
